in this video we're going to talk about
the doppler effect
the doppler effect is a phenomenon where
the frequency
that is detected by some observer
changes because either the source is
moving or the observer is moving
so let's say
we have a source
and this source
emits sound waves in all directions
and let's say we have an observer
if the source
moves towards the observer
or if the observer moves towards the
source of the sound waves
the frequency
that is detected by the observer that's
ethyl
that frequency is going to increase
which means the frequency measured by
the observer will be greater than the
frequency of the source
so let me give an example of some
numbers
so let's say you have a source that's
moving
towards this person
the source may have a frequency of
800 hertz
but the frequency that the person will
hear is going to be higher than 800
it might be 850 hertz
and so that's the basic idea behind the
doppler effect
whenever the source or the observer is
moving
the detected frequency is going to shift
it's going to be different than the
original frequency that the source
emitted
so whenever the source
or the observer
moves toward each other
the observed frequency is going to be
bigger than the source frequency
now the reverse is true let's say if the
source
is moving away from the observer or
if the observer is moving away from the
source
then the frequency that the observer
detects
that's going to decrease
which means that it's going to be less
than the original frequency emanated or
emitted by the source
now let's draw a picture
so here's the source
and we're going to draw some waves
around the source
okay my drawing's not perfect but we'll
make the best of that
let's make one more wave
so let's say we have a person here
we'll say this is john
and to the left
is karen
now
the source of the sound wave this could
be like an ambush trunk or
a police car
this is moving towards john
and let's say that the frequency emitted
by the source
is
1000 hertz
john
let's say john and karen are stationary
observers they're not moving
so their speed their
vo is zero
now as the source of the sound moves
towards john
the frequency that john is gonna hear
is going to be higher
than a thousand it might be eleven
hundred
now the source is moving away from karen
so the frequency that karen detects
is going to be less than a thousand it's
going to be like maybe 900 or 800
and let's talk about why
as the source moves toward john
notice that the distance
between
the crest of the waves is decreasing so
therefore the wavelength is decreasing
whenever the wavelength decreases
the frequency increases so that's one of
the reasons why
the frequency increases as the source
moves towards john
is because the distance between
waves
is decreasing
but now as the source moves away from
karen
we can see that the distance between the
waves
is increasing
so as the wavelength goes up
the frequency goes down
so anytime the source moves away from a
person
the frequency is going to go down
because the wavelength is increasing but
when the source moves towards a person
the wavelength decreases and so the
frequency goes up
so that's a visual representation of how
the doppler effect work when the source
is moving and the observer is stationary
but now let's talk about the formula
that we could use to solve problems
the observed
frequency is equal to the frequency of
the source
times v
and then it's
plus or minus
v naught
over v and then you could write this as
plus or minus or minus plus
you can still get the right answer
regardless of how you choose to write
the write the equation
but what you need to realize is that v
is the speed of sound
which is 343 meters per second
now the speed of sound in air
is dependent on the temperature
and here's the formula that describes
that relationship
the speed of sound is
approximately 331
plus
0.6 t
where t is the temperature in celsius
and v is going to be the speed in meters
per second
so at a temperature of zero degrees
celsius
this disappears you simply get a speed
of
approximately 331
meters per second
when a temperature is 20 degrees celsius
based on that equation
the speed is let me use the approximate
symbol
it's approximately 343 meters per second
and at 25 degrees celsius
the speed
is approximately 346 meters per second
so the speed increases by 26 meters per
second for every
increase in one degree celsius in
temperature
when the temperature increases by 5
degrees celsius the speed
increases approximately by three meters
per second
so that's the formula that would help
you to get an estimate of the speed of
sound in air given the temperature
but if the temperature is not specified
we're going to assume that the
temperature is at 20 degrees celsius so
we're going to go with this number
so if you're not given the temperature
or the speed of sound simply use 343
meters per second for the problems that
we're going to solve in this video
now in order to use this equation
successfully you need to know when to
use the positive side
and the negative sign in the numerator
and in the denominator of that fraction
so how do we choose
when to use what sign
well we need to have an understanding of
fractions
a fraction is made up of two parts
there is the numerator
on the top
and the denominator on the bottom
now what you need to know is that the
value of the numerator is proportional
to the value of the fraction so what
does that mean
when you increase the value of the
numerator the value of the fraction goes
up
so in that sense they're proportional
what happens to one happens to the other
if you decrease the value of the
numerator
the value of the fraction goes down
now the situation is different for the
denominator of a fraction
the denominator is inversely related to
the value of the entire fraction that
means when one goes up the other goes
down so if you were to increase the
value of the denominator
the value of the entire fraction
decreases
and if you decrease the value of the
denominator the value of the entire
fraction increases
so make sure you understand that
relationship
feel free to write this down because
we're going to use it to talk about when
to use these signs
so let's consider the first situation
that is when the source
is moving
towards the observer
so vs
represents the speed
of the source
vo
represents the speed of the observer
if the observer is stationary that means
vo is zero
if the source is stationary that means
vs zero
but let's say in this situation the
observer is stationary but the source is
moving towards the observer
what sign should we use in front of vs
should it be positive or negative
so the fact that the source is moving
towards the observer what's going to
happen to the frequency that is fo
any time one moves towards the other do
we know the frequency is going to be
higher
fo
is going to increase
now vs is in the denominator of the
fraction
so if we want the whole
fraction to increase
should we increase the denominator or
should we decrease it
well we know the denominator is
inversely related to
the value of the fraction so if we want
the value of the entire fraction to go
up
we need the denominator to go down
so therefore the only way we can
decrease the value
of the denominator is to use a negative
in front of the s
so when the source moves towards the
observer
we're going to use negative vs
that's going to decrease the value of
the denominator which will increase the
value of the fraction and so the
observed frequency is going to be higher
than the source frequency
now let's consider the other situation
that is
when the source
moves away from the observer
when the source moves away from the
observer we know that the frequency that
is observed or detected by the observer
that has to go down
the source velocity is still in the
bottom of the fraction
it's still in the denominator
so the only way we can
decrease the value of the entire
fraction to get a lower fo value
is to increase the value of the
denominator
so we need to use positive
vs
if we increase the value of the
denominator the value of the whole
fraction goes down fo becomes less than
fs
now let's consider the next situation
so here we have the source
and this time the observer
is going to move
toward the source
now when the observer moves towards the
source we know that the detected
frequency is going to increase
and we're dealing with vo now not vs and
vo is in the numerator
of
the fraction
so should we use positive vo or negative
vo
what would you say
well since fo is going to increase the
value of the entire fraction has to go
up
and to accomplish that using the
numerator we need the numerator to
increase
so therefore we need to use a positive
sign for vo that's going to increase the
numerator
now what about
if the observer
is moving away from the source
if he's moving away
f o is going to decrease
so in order to decrease the value of the
whole fraction we need to decrease the
numerator
so therefore we need to use the negative
sign
in front of
vo
so let's put this all together in one
page
and what i'm going to do is i'm going to
reverse the position of the source and
the observer because
the signs of v will correspond to the
direction of the arrow along the x-axis
so in this situation
we're going to have the source moving
towards the observer
and when that happens
we're going to use negative
vs
notice that the arrow is pointing
towards the left if you put the source
on the right and the observer on the
left
the direction of the arrow is going to
correspond to the sign in front of v so
when the source moves towards the person
use negative vs
the denominator will decrease
and the value of the fraction and thus
the detector frequency will go up
now for the next scenario
the source
is moving away
from the observer
so we're going to use
positive vs
notice that the arrow
is pointing towards the right
in the positive x direction
so in this case the denominator is going
to increase in value the frequency is
going to decrease in value
now for the next situation
here's the observer
and this time the observer is going to
move
towards the source
as the observer moves towards the source
we know that the detective frequency is
going to go up
and so the numerator has to go up
thus
we need to use positive
vo now for the fourth situation the
observer is moving away
from the source
so the detective frequency is going to
go down
and the numerator must go down in order
to accomplish that
so this is going to be negative vo
so as you can see when you place the
observer on the left and the source on
the right
the sign in front of v corresponds to
the direction of the arrow
so it's negative going towards the left
positive going towards the right if we
put the observer on the left and the
source on the right
that's only when it's going to work out
that way
but any time
the source or the observer
moves toward one another
in all cases
we see that
the observed frequency increases
and whenever either the source
or the observer
moves away from each other
the detected frequency
decreases
so make sure you understand that concept
of the doppler effect
so now let's work on some problems
number one
an ambulance truck emits a sound with a
frequency of 800 hertz
part a what is the frequency detected by
a stationary observer if the ambulance
truck is moving
30 meters per second toward the observer
and we're given the speed of sound and
air at 20 degrees celsius which is 343
meters per second
so let's go ahead and work on this
problem let's draw a picture
now it's going to make it a lot easier
if we put the observer on the left
and we're going to put the source
on the right
the source is going to be the ambulance
truck
it's emitting a sound
with a frequency of 800 hertz
the frequency
is also related to the pitch they're the
same
so a sound with a high pitch has a high
frequency
now this ambulance truck which is the
source
it's moving towards the observer
and here's the formula fo is equal to fs
and then it's v plus or minus
vs
i mean that should be vo
over v plus or minus vs
so we need to determine if vs should be
positive or negative
so the arrow points towards the left
vs is going to be a negative
so if we choose a negative value
we know that the denominator
is going to decrease
and the value of the whole fraction and
thus fo is going to increase
which is what should happen whenever the
source moves towards the observer the
detected frequency should go up
so now that we know which sign we need
to use we can
go ahead and get the answer
so the source frequency is 800
the speed of sound is 343.
the observer is stationary
so he's not moving anywhere
vo is zero
and then vs we're going to use a
negative value the source is moving
towards the observer at 30 meters per
second
so this is going to be 800
times 343 and then 343 minus 30
that's 313.
so the detected frequency measured by
the observer
is approximately
877 hertz
so this is the answer
to part a
now let's move on to part b
what frequency will be detected if the
ambulance truck is moving
30 meters per second away from the
observer
so we still want the source to be to the
right of the observer
and let's rewrite the equation
now what should we use for the sign of
vs
so the arrow is pointing towards the
right this is going to be positive
vs
so this works
if you put the observer on the left and
the source on the right
now as we can see when if we choose a
positive sign for vs
the denominator will increase in value
and so the value of the whole fraction
is going to go down
and the source as it moves away from
the observer we expect that the detected
frequency or the observed frequency
should be less
than the original source frequency
so let's go ahead and get the answer
the source frequency is still 800
the speed of sound is still 343
vo is still 0 but this time we're going
to use positive vs
and vs is 30.
so it's going to be 800
times 343
and then 343 plus 30 that's 373.
so this is going to be
and 736 hertz
so as you can see it's less than 800
which is what should happen
when the source moves away from the
observer the pitch or the frequency
should decrease
so that's how you can solve some basic
doppler effect
problems in physics
number two
a stationary ambulance truck emits a
frequency of 1200 hertz
calculate the frequency detected by the
observer
if
the observer is driving toward the
ambulance truck
at 25 meters per second
so let's begin with a picture
we're going to put the observer on the
left side
just like before
and we're going to put the source on the
right side
now in this problem the observer is
moving towards the source
now let's write our formula
so we need to determine if we're going
to use positive
or negative
vo
so what would you say should it be plus
vo or minus vo
well because the observer is moving
towards the source
and for this particular situation it's
going to be plus
vo
and here's how we can reason
like we've been reasoning before
as the observer moves towards the source
we know that the detective frequency has
to go up
and since the vo is in the numerator
the only way in which we can increase
the detected frequency
using the numerator is to increase the
numerator
and that can only happen if we use
positive vo
so now that we know the sign of vo we
can plug in
the data that we have
so the source frequency is 1200
v
in this problem is 343
the source is stationary so vs is zero
and then vo
is moving at 25 meters per second so
that's the observer
now 343 plus 25
that's going to be 368
and we're going to divide that by 343
so for part a
the frequency measured by the observer
is going to be
1287.46 but let's round that to nearest
whole number
so we'll say 1287 hertz
so that's the frequency that the driver
is going to detect
as he moves towards the amblin struck
now let's move on to part b
in part b the observer is driving away
from the ambulance truck so this time
he's going in this direction
so it's going to be negative
vs
because he's moving away
we know that the detective frequency
will decrease
relative to the source frequency
and to accomplish that we need to
decrease the numerator
so we need to use
i put vs i meant to put vo
so we need to use a negative
vo
so let's go ahead and plug that in
so the source frequency is still 1200
v is still 343
vs is still zero but the only thing
that's different here is we're going to
plug in a negative
vo which is
so it's going to be negative 25.
343 minus 25 is 318.
so it's going to be 1200 times 318
divided by 343
and so for part b
the frequency picked up by the observer
it's going to be if you round it to the
nearest whole number 1113
hertz
so as you can see it's less
than 1200 because
the driver is moving away
but for the first part it's greater than
1200 because
the drive is moving towards
uh the source of the sound
now let's move on to the next problem
number three
a police car is moving west at 20 meters
per second
toward a driver who is moving east at 25
meters per second
the police car emits a frequency of 900
hertz
what frequency is detected by the driver
so feel free to try this problem for the
sake of practice
now let's draw a picture
so as long as we place the observer on
the left side
and the source
on the right side
the signs
of vo and vs
they're going to match with the
direction
of the velocity
of these two objects
along the x-axis
now
the police car
which is basically the source of the
sound
it's going to
be moving west
so it's going this way
at a speed of
20 meters per second
now the driver
is moving east or towards the right at a
speed of 25 meters per second
so automatically
because we have the observer on the left
and a source and a right the direction
of the arrow is going to be the same
as
it's going to be aligned with the sign
of vo and vs
so we're going to use a positive value
for vo
and a negative value
for vs
and just to confirm it
the observer is moving towards the
source so that action will increase
the detected frequency
vo is in the numerator of the fraction
so in order to increase the frequency we
need to increase the value of the
numerator and so we need to choose a
positive value for vo as opposed to a
negative value
now the action taken by the source as it
moves towards the observer
that action will also
increase the detected frequency
vs is in the denominator
of the formula
and in order to increase the value of
the fraction we need to decrease
the value of the denominator and we can
accomplish that by using negative es
so i want you to understand how that
works
because that can help you
to choose the appropriate sign
if these two are not in the
the right position
so now that we have everything that we
need
let's go ahead and plug it in
to
our formula
so the observed frequency is going to
equal the source frequency
which in this problem
that's 900 hertz
and then that's going to be 343.
now we're going to use plus
vo
so the speed of the observer
is 25 meters per second
and then we're going to use minus vs
the speed of the source or the police
car is moving 20 meters per second west
so this is going to be 900
343 plus 25 we know that's
368.
343 minus 20 that's
323.
so 900 times 368 divided by 323.
so we get this answer
the observed frequency is going to be 1
25 hertz
so as we can see it's significantly
higher
than
the source frequency of 900
because both
the source and the observer are moving
toward each other so that's going to
greatly increase
the frequency that is detected by the
observer
you